Edmund L. Nichols papers, Inclusive: circa 1913-2010, Bulk: 1941-2009
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Edmund L. Nichols papers
Inclusive: circa 1913-2010, Bulk: 1941-2009
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
64
Nichols, Edmund L.
14 document boxes and 7 oversized boxes
The Edmund L. Nichols papers encompass the government career of Ed Nichols, including his service with the Texas Department of Agriculture, the U.S. Department of Agriculture, and diplomatic service abroad as a U.S. agricultural counselor in several European countries. The collection also includes personal papers and correspondence.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Edmund L. Nichols was born in Throckmorton, Texas, December 18, 1931. He attended Throckmorton High School, graduating in 1949, and then furthered his education in music at Hardin-Simmons University in Abilene, 1953. He is recognized as a Distinguished Alumnus at both schools. Nichols then attended the University of Texas at Austin, earning a master’s degree in music education, 1957. He married Sandra K. Heiligman in 1964, and they have three children: Dr. Jill E. Nichols, James E. Nichols, and Kelly R. Nichols Jones. They have six grandchildren and live in Austin.
During his undergraduate years at Hardin-Simmons, Nichols gained parallel experience in journalism, working full-time at the Abilene Reporter-News. After a brief period of teaching choral music in Pampa, Texas, he was employed by United Press news wire service, first in Dallas and then, in early 1955, to help cover the Texas legislative session and the inauguration of Governor Allan Shivers in Austin. As that session ended, Nichols was invited to join the staff of Texas Agriculture Commissioner John C. White as a technical writer.
After a brief hiatus from 1959 to 1961, when Nichols lived and worked in Hawaii, he rejoined the staff of Commissioner White, working from 1961 to 1965 as Administrative Assistant, then as Assistant Commissioner of Agriculture for Texas, 1965-1977. In 1977, White moved to Washington, D. C. and Nichols followed suit as the newly appointed Assistant Deputy Secretary of the U.S. Department of Agriculture. His D.C. career also included serving as the Foreign Agricultural Service (FAS) Information and Legislative Officer, 1978-1979. He also represented Agriculture on President Carter’s Export Policy Task Force and was named by President Carter to be a charter member of the U.S. Senior Executive Service.
The next chapter in Nichols’ agriculture career involved his appointment by the U.S. Secretary of Agriculture to several overseas posts. Nichols moved to Rome, Italy in 1979 as the U.S. Agricultural Counselor to Italy and was commissioned by President Reagan to the rank of Minister-Counselor in the U.S. Senior Foreign Service. The President of Italy decorated Nichols as Commendatore of the Italian Republic for his role in advancing U.S.-Italian trade relations. In 1982, Nichols transferred to Copenhagen to serve as U.S. Agricultural Counselor to Denmark and Norway, and again in 1985 to Madrid, Spain. From 1989-1992, he served as Agricultural Minister-Counselor to the U.S. Mission to the European Communities in Brussels, Belgium. His last assignment in Europe before retiring involved one more year as U.S. Agricultural Counselor in Madrid, 1992-1993. During the course of his service in Europe, Nichols served as chairman of the NATO Food and Agriculture Planning Committee, formed to plan security for Europe and America in the event of war.
Scope and Content
The Edmund L. Nichols papers, 1913-2010, cover a significant span of Nichols’ public and personal life. This collection includes public and personal correspondence and photographs, speeches, mementos, and records from Nichols’ public service with the Texas Department of Agriculture, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Foreign Agricultural Service, and diplomatic service abroad in Italy, Denmark and Norway, Spain, and Belgium. There is also a significant portion of material related to his education and reunions with Throckmorton High School and Hardin-Simmons University, Abilene, Texas. The bulk of the material spans 1941-2009.
The Nichols papers are arranged in four series. Series I, Texas Department of Agriculture, includes Nichols service in the Texas Department of Agriculture under Commissioner John C. White. Materials pertaining to this service include records, speeches, and other event items from Texas food products promotion, photos from a People-to-People tour to Europe and the Soviet Union, and photos, documents, and correspondence from involvement in the Japan-Texas Association Conference. Nichols also served briefly under White in the U. S. Department of Agriculture before taking a position in the U.S.D.A. Foreign Agricultural Service. These materials are found in Series II, U.S. Department of Agriculture, and include photos of his trip to China, as well as correspondence, records, speeches, and other related items.
Series III, Diplomatic Service, is the largest series and includes materials from the 14 years Nichols spent in Europe with the Foreign Agricultural Service as an Agricultural Counselor in Rome, Copenhagen, and Madrid. In Brussels, he held a position as Agricultural Minister-Counselor with the U.S. Mission to the European Communities. Many invitations, photographs, records, public and personal correspondence, and travel mementos can be found in this series.
The Nichols papers also include personal material surrounding the life and family of Ed Nichols. These items are located in Series IV, Personal, and include correspondence, photographs, family history, music and drama books, high school and college materials, diplomas, reunion records and photos, and speeches and essays. Of particular note is his correspondence with Sarah Ragle Weddington.
Arrangement
The Edmund L. Nichols papers are arranged in four series: I. Texas Department of Agriculture, II. U.S. Department of Agriculture, III. Diplomatic Service, IV. Personal.
Series III, Diplomatic Service, has five subseries: 1. General, II. Rome, Italy, III. Copenhagen, Denmark, IV. Madrid, Spain, and V. Brussels, Belgium. Series IV, Personal, has two subseries: I. General and II. Correspondence.
The papers are arranged topically and loosely chronologically, principally using the original order in which they arrived.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 64. Acquired 2010-06-14
Related Resources
Related references
“Edmund Lowe Nichols.” Texas State Cemetery..
Edmund L. Nichols papers, Accession #64, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W. R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Nichols family -- Archives.; Nichols, Edmund L. -- Archives.; Nichols, Edmund.; Weddington, Sarah Ragle.; White, J. C. (John C.)
Subjects (Organizations)
European Economic Community -- United States.; Texas. Department of Agriculture.; United States. Department of Agriculture -- Officials and employees -- Archives.; United States. Department of Agriculture.; United States. Foreign Agricultural Service.
Places
Belgium -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Denmark -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Italy -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Norway -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Spain -- Foreign relations -- United States.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Belgium.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Denmark.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Italy.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Norway.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Spain.
Subjects
Agricultural attachés -- United States.; Foreign trade promotion -- United States.
Genres
35 mm negative film (color); Photographic print; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Records (Documents); Speeches.
- Texas Department of Agriculture, 1955-1978, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains materials relating to Nichols’ roles in the Texas Department of Agriculture in Austin as Administrative Assistant, 1961-1965, and Assistant Commissioner of Agriculture for Texas, 1965-1977. As Assistant Commissioner to John C. White, he played a key role in promoting Texas food products, including the launch of the Texas Agricultural Products (TAP) export marketing program which hosted “Taste of Texas” events in other states. He also traveled widely, marketing Texas produce and meat products in Japan and Europe. Of notable interest in this series are biographies, speeches, photographs, office stationery, event nametags, and items related to a People-to-People tour and the Japan-Texas Association Conference. This series is in good condition.
  - Biographical, Assistant Commissioner of Agriculture for Texas, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical, Assistant Commissioner of Agriculture for Texas, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Speeches and Press Releases, circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publications, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Ed Nichols, circa 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Credential Cards, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Event Nametags, Badges, Ribbons, 1974-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1973-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Texas State Agricultural Leaders People-to-People Travel to Europe and the Soviet Union, 1967 July 26-August 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Texas State Agricultural Leaders People-to-People Travel to Europe and the Soviet Union Photographs, 1967 July 26-August 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Japan-Texas Association Conference, 1972 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Japan-Texas Association Conference Photographs, 1972-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Japan-Texas Association Conference, 1971 July-1977 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Japan-Texas Association Conference, 1972 May-1977 January (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Assistant Commissioner of Agriculture for Texas, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Southern Commissioners of Agriculture, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Texas State Agency Business Administrators Association President, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Texas Department of Agriculture yellow ballpoint pen, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Ed Nichols Business Card Holder, black leather, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Texas State Agency Business Administrators’ Association, President 1970-1971 wooden plaque (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 1)
- U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1970-1987, undated; 2
  This series holds items related to Nichols’ roles in the U.S. Department of Agriculture in Washington, D.C. as Assistant to the Deputy Secretary, 1977-1978, and U.S.D.A. Foreign Agricultural Service (FAS) Information and Legislative Officer, 1978-1979. As Assistant to the Deputy Secretary, he again worked for John C. White and traveled widely, including to China in 1978 to assist in normalization of trade relations. Notably, Nichols worked with Congressman W. R. Poage to pass the U.S. Agricultural Trade Act of 1978, which improved diplomatic relations for the U.S.D.A. internationally. Within this series are biographies, correspondence, administrative materials, photographs, event nametags, speeches, memos, and items related to Nichols’s trip to China. This series is in good condition.
  - John C. White, Deputy Secretary of Agriculture Promotion, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Government Position Applications, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Business Cards and Office Nameplates, circa 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Resumés, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Nichols and White Memos, 1977 June-October (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs in Office of the Secretary of Agriculture, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Position Appointment Announcement News clippings, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Market Development Teams in Eastern Europe, 1978 April-August (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Event Nametags, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Certificates, Foreign Service Institute, Department of State, 1979 June (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Work and Invitations in D.C., 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Positive Incoming Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Speaking Engagements and Speeches, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Speeches, 1970, 1978 June-August (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Western U.S. Agriculture Trip with Vice President Walter Mondale, 1978 January (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Senior Executive Service Management System, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Visit to People’s Republic of China (1 of 4), 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Visit to People’s Republic of China (2 of 4), 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Visit to People’s Republic of China (3 of 4), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Visit to People’s Republic of China (4 of 4), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Visit to People’s Republic of China Photographs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Assistant to the Administrator of the Foreign Agricultural Service (FAS), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Foreign Agricultural Service (FAS) Memos, 1978 May-November (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Working Group on Agricultural Policy, Export Policy Task Force, 1978 April-August (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Agricultural Trade Act of 1978, 1978 May-August (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Grain Export Restriction News Release, 1978 July 20 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture, 3-D official seal, undated (Box 16 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Secretary of Agriculture clear digital thermometer and silver pen in brown box, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - National Potato Council silver foldable pocket-knife and nail file, 1977 December (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture Seal gold-plated medallion, Compliments of the U.S. Secretary of Agriculture Richard E. Lyng, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture Seal pin in white box, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - Compliments of U.S. Secretary of Agriculture black and silver ballpoint pen, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 7)
- Diplomatic Service, 1967-2010, undated; 3
  This series encompasses Nichols’s diplomatic service with the U.S. Foreign Agricultural Service as U.S. Agricultural Counselor. He served in this capacity in four locations: Rome, Italy; Copenhagen, Denmark and Oslo, Norway; Madrid, Spain; and Brussels, Belgium.
  - General, 1967-2008, undated; 1
    Subseries I. General, covers Nichols’ entire foreign diplomatic service from 1979-1993. It pertains to general materials needed for foreign travel and service in the U.S.D.A., including passports and identification, records, nametags and invitations, and family pet information. It also includes items related to the European Union Conference in 1995.
    - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) Food and Agricultural Committee, 1979-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Passport Copies, 1982-2008 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Foreign Driving Permit Copies, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - U.S.D.A. Travel Authorization, 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Food Purchase Orders and Planning, 1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Foreign Agricultural Service Records, 1977-1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Passports, Ed Nichols, 1972-1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Passports, Sandy Nichols, 1979-1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Diplomatic Identity Cards, 1979-1997 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Diplomatic Passports and Identification, 1979-2008 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Pets Abroad, 1967-1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Agricultural Counselor Business Cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Embassies in Copenhagen and Rome, 1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Nametags, 1979-1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Blank Letterhead and Stationery, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Appointment Announcements and Travel Vaccine Records, 1976-1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - European Union Conference, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 16 Years of Service Award, Foreign Agricultural Service, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1993 October (Box 15 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Senior Executive Service Admission, 1979 July (Box 17 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Foreign Service Officer Appointment Certificate, 1981 November (Box 17 OVZ, Folder 2)
    - Minister-Counselor Presidential Appointment, 1981 September 28 (Box 17 OVZ, Folder 3)
    - Consular Officer and Secretary in the Diplomatic Service Presidential Appointment, 1981 September 28 (Box 17 OVZ, Folder 4)
    - Business Cards, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 8)
    - U.S. Department of Agriculture, Ten-Year Service Award, 1987 November (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 2)
    - NATO Senior Civil Emergency Planning Committee Service Award, 1981-1985 (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Rome, Italy, 1978-1988, undated; 2
    Subseries II. Rome, Italy, spans 1979-1982, and covers Nichols’ first foreign diplomatic service abroad as U.S. Agricultural Counselor to Italy. He was decorated by the President of Italy in 1982, as Commendatore (a high Italian honorific title) for advancing U.S. — Italian trade relations. Nichols successfully deliberated with the Italian Minister of Agriculture about not raising tariffs on U.S. exports. Of interest in this subseries are invitations and guest lists for parties and events, travel mementos, public correspondence and official business documents, and personal correspondence and photographs. Subseries II contains some Italian language material.
    - Appointment to Counselor for Agricultural Affairs, 1981 October (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Invitations and Guest Lists, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Performance Appraisal, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Palazzo Della Valle Booklet, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Selva di Meana Cork Menu, 1981 July 15 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Personal Correspondence and Invitations, 1979-1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence and Work (1 of 2), 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence and Work (2 of 2), 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence and Work, 1979-1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Personal Correspondence and Photographs, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, circa 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and Mementos, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Roman Apartment Floor Plans, undated (Box 17 OVZ, Folder 5)
    - Commissione Interministeriale Rifornimenti, Roma, personalized bronze medallion in blue box, 1984 December (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 9)
    - Associazione Nazionale Stampa Agricola medallion, inscribed: Al Consigliere, Edmund Nichols, Roma, in blue box, 1982 January 14 (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 10)
    - Associazione Italiana Quarter Horse, Honorary Member Card, in black box, undated (Box 18 OVZ, Folder 11)
    - Italian Society for Zootechnic Progress, Milan, Honorary Member Award, 1980 April 17 (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 4)
    - The Italian Newspaper of Europe, 1980 (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - Copenhagen, Denmark, 1982-1986, undated; 3
    Subseries III. Copenhagen, Denmark, spans Nichols’ role as U.S. Agricultural Counselor to Denmark and Norway from 1982-1985. Of notable interest in this subseries are invitations and guest lists for parties and events, travel mementos, public correspondence and official business documents, and personal correspondence and photographs. Furthermore, two interesting folders cover Vice President George H. W. Bush’s visit to Denmark, and a visit to Lapland in northern Norway. Subseries III contains some Danish language material.
    - Auto Papers, 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Personal Correspondence and Photographs, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - BP Language Book, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Vice President George H. W. Bush Visits Denmark, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Invitations and Guest Lists, 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - United States Department of Agriculture (U.S.D.A.) and Foreign Agricultural Service Business, 1983-1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Biographical, 1983 July 1 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence and Mementos, 1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence and Mementos, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Carpet Square Memento, 1984 July (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Printed Plastic Bag Mementos, 1985, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence, Work, and Photos, 1982-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence and Work (1 of 2), 1982-1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence and Work (2 of 2), 1982-1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Invitations and Guest Lists, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Lapland Visit, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - “Food from Texas” Dinner Menu, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Invitations (1 of 2), 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Invitations (2 of 2), 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Invitations, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Residence Photographs, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Cote d’Ivoire Postcards, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, 1982-1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - South and West Jutland Agricultural Country Fair plate, 1983 (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - Madrid, Spain, 1982-2010, undated; 4
    Subseries IV. Madrid, Spain, covers both of Nichols’ appointments as U.S. Agricultural Counselor to Spain, 1985-1989 and 1992-1993. Both appointments are arranged together in this subseries and can be distinguished by the folder and document dates. Materials in this subseries include biographies, invitations and guest lists for parties and events, travel mementos, public correspondence and official business documents, activities reports, and personal correspondence and photographs. Subseries IV contains some Spanish language material.
    - Photographs, 1984-1992, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Biographical, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - U.S. Agricultural Counselor Correspondence, Photos, and Mementos, 1985-1994 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Invitations and Guest Lists, 1983-1989, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Pet Vaccination Information, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Position Evaluations, 1985-1989 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Photographs, 1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - King of Spain Photographs, 1986-1991 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - News Clippings, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Position Papers, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Daily Activities Report, 1986 October-December (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Daily Activities Report, 1987 January-December (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Daily and Weekly Activities Report, 1988 January-1989 June (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Photographs, 1987-1988, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Personal Correspondence and Mementos, 1982-1992 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Invitations and Guest Lists, 1985-1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Rioja Weekend Trip, 1993-2010 (Box 8, Folder 4)